Dr Nivaas, MD Psychiatry (NIMHANS)

Namakkal, Tamil Nadu

drnivasnimhans@gmail.com

+91-7373721676

linkedin.com/in/dr-nivaas-saminathan-1837a1109

https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Dr-S-S-3

Summary

I did my post graduation from the department of psychiatry at NIMHANS, one of the leading institutes in the field of mental health and neurosciences in India, where I provide quality care to patients with various mental health conditions in both outpatient and inpatient setting.

With three years of work experience in the field of psychiatry, I have developed skills in diagnosis, treatment, counseling, and research. My core competencies include clinical assessment, emergency psychiatry, psychotherapy, psychopharmacology, and crisis intervention.

I am passionate about improving the mental well-being of my patients and advancing the knowledge and practice of psychiatry. My goal is to become a competent and compassionate psychiatrist who can contribute to the field and the society.

Languages known: Tamil, Kannada, English

My Areas of Interest: General Psychiatry, Child Psychiatry, Addiction Psychiatry, Neuromodulation,

Neuropsychiatry, CLP

Expected Job: Consultant Neuropsychiatrist

Experience



Junior Resident In Psychiatry

National Institute of Mental Health and Neuro Sciences (NIMHANS), India Jan 2021 - Dec 2023 (3 years) In addition to general psychiatric services:

I had exposure in the different specialty clinics of schizophrenia and metabolic clinic, obsessivecompulsive disorder clinic, perinatal clinic and geriatric special clinic

During the course, also had 100 hours of supervised psychotherapy sessions under Prof. Muralidharan Kesavan

In addition, delivered supervised family therapy and behavioral therapy sessions under respective family and behavioral therapy units.

Attended multiple sub-specialties for 3 months each in child adolescent psychiatry, Centre of addiction medicine, consultation-liaison psychiatry and neurology.

My thesis under the supervision of Prof. Jagadisha Thirthalli got approval from the review committee in November 2023 (Title: "Effect of Reducing Pulse Width and Pulse Frequency of Electrical Stimulus on Clinical Response to Electroconvulsive Therapy (ECT)- A Retrospective Chart Review"

Have passed my MD psychiatry Exit Exam held in December 2023, with good scores

Casualty medical officer (CMO)

National Institute of Mental Health and Neuro Sciences (NIMHANS), India Jul 2020 - Oct 2020 (4 months)

Skilled in screening patients in Neurocasualty, Triage, providing emergency care and life support and referring to Neurology/ Neurosurgery emergency team

Non PG Junior resident in the Department of Neurophysiology

National Institute of Mental Health and Neuro Sciences (NIMHANS), India Apr 2020 - Jun 2020 (3 months)

Trained in performing and reporting various neurophysiological tests- AFT, Tilt table test, Sweat analysis test,

Senior house surgeon (Surgery)

Integral Coach Factory (ICF) Hospital, Chennai

Jun 2019 - Dec 2019 (7 months)

Skilled in minor OT procedures, assisting in major surgical procedures, seeing OP patients · Inpatient Care

House surgeon

Karpagam Faculty of Medical Sciences and Research, Coimbatore Oct 2017 - Oct 2018 (1 year 1 month)

Compulsory Rotatory Residential Internship under various specialties and sub-specialties

Education

Green Park matric & higher secondary school, Namakkal, Tamil Nadu

High School/Secondary Certificate Programs, Junior High/Intermediate/Middle School Education and Teaching

2007 - 2012

Karpagam Faculty of Medical Sciences and Research, Coimbatore

Bachelor of Medicine, Bachelor of Surgery (MBBS), Medicine 2012 - 2017

National Institute of Mental Health and Neuro Sciences (NIMHANS), India

MD Psychiatry, Psychiatry Residency Program, Psychiatry Residency Program 2021 - 2023

Skills

Addiction Psychiatry • Child Psychiatry • Psychiatry • CLP

Honors & Awards

Best House Surgeon Award - Karpagam Faculty of Medical Sciences and Research, Coimbatore 2018